Guide to the Philip Thorpe Property Settlement Papers 1875-1880
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Philip Thorpe Property Settlement Papers
1875-1880
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Thorpe, Philip, b. 1829
2478
1 folder
The Philip Thorpe Property Settlement Papers consist of letters sent by Sweeney to Thorpe with detailed instructions on handling livestock on the property and what improvements to pay for. Also included is a schoolgirl's letter, likely written by Aline ("Ellen") Anceney, regarding a school at Spring Hill, and a letter from Episcopal priest Frank B. Lewis inquiring about local interest in a church service to be held in Thorpe's area.
Folder 1
Philip Thorpe was born in England on May 8, 1829 and came to America in 1849, visiting New York and Wisconsin before traveling to California during the gold rush. He came to Bannack, Montana Territory, in 1863 and in 1864 settled in the Gallatin Valley near the town of Hamilton, Gallatin County. There Thorpe ran a dairy and cattle operation until 1880 when he moved to Dillon in Beaverhead County. During the mid 1870s, Thorpe acted as an agent for John M. Sweeney and the T.C. Power and Company in connection with a lawsuit between Charles Spafford and Sweeney. The lawsuit culminated in early 1876 with a judgment in favor of Sweeney, and Thorpe was retained as an agent to deal with William Perks, a tenant on the land claimed by Sweeney.
The documents in this collection consist mostly of letters sent by Sweeney to Thorpe with detailed instructions on handling livestock on the property and what improvements to pay for. Also included is a schoolgirl's letter, likely written by Aline ("Ellen") Anceney, regarding a school at Spring Hill, and a letter from Episcopal priest Frank B. Lewis inquiring about local interest in a church service to be held in Thorpe's area.
This collection is open for research.
The Philip Thorpe papers were purchased by the Montana State University Library Special Collections from Charles Apfelbaum of Watchung, New Jersey, on May 9, 2005.
Anceney, Aline-Correspondence; Lewis, Frank B., b. ca. 1844-Correspondence; Perks, William, b. ca. 1833; Sweeney, John M., 1842-1887
Gallatin County (Mont.)-Religious life and customs
Landlord and tenant-Montana-Gallatin County; Schools-Montana-Springhill
Elementary and Secondary Education; Ranching; Religion; Montana
- John M. Sweeney (Helena, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe, 1875 February 6 (Folder 1)
  Letter referring to difficulties between Charles Spafford and Elijah M. Dumphey regarding livestock.
- John M. Sweeney (Helena, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe, 1875 February 25 (Folder 1)
  Letter directing Thorpe to make an agreement with William Perks for management of the property. Mentions T.C. Power and his trip to Corinne, Utah Territory.
- J. J. Davis (Bozeman, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe, 1876 January 11 (Folder 1)
  Letter advising that Davis had ordered the Gallatin County Sheriff to proceed with the sale and settlement of the Sweeney vs. Spafford lawsuit.
- Memoranda of agreement between Sweeney and Thorpe, with listing of duties for property assumed by William Perks. Likely was included with letter of February 27, 1876 January 23 (Folder 1)
- John M. Sweeney (Helena, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe, 1876 January 26 (Folder 1)
  Letter responding to Thorpe's report of the sheriff's sale of the Spafford property and promise to follow up with instructions for an agreement with William Perks.
- Statement of expenses in probate court case of John M. Sweeney vs. Charles Spafford, signed by Gallatin County Sheriff Silas Ralston., 1876 February 5 (Folder 1)
- John M. Sweeney (Helena, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe, 1876 February 27 (Folder 1)
  Letter forwarding a memoranda of agreement for the disposition of livestock and property currently occupied by William Perks. Particular detail on horse breeding.
- John M. Sweeney (Helena, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe, 1876 March 12 (Folder 1)
  Letter instructing Thorpe on the details of an agreement with William Perks, a farm or ranch tenant, clarifying the disposition of cattle assigned to Perks.
- Memoranda of agreement between Sweeney and Thorpe, with listing of duties for property assumed by William Perks and inventory of farm tools turned over to Perks, 1876 March (Folder 1)
- Ellen [Aline?] Anceney (Spring Hill, [Montana Territory]) to "Dear Friend", 1877 September 19 (Folder 1)
  Girl's letter describing school, church, and a party held at Mr. Spaffords.
- G. F. Cope (Meadow Creek, [Montana Territory]) to Philip Thorpe, 1879 January 20 (Folder 1)
  Letter with offer to sell shorthorn cattle for breeding; details on cattle pedigree linage.
- W. O. P. Hays (Helena, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe, 1879 January 22 (Folder 1)
  Letter mentioning upcoming legislation regarding the "punch law."
- Davenport & Ray (Helena, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe, 1879 January 23 (Folder 1)
  Letter advising that Mr. Gordon will not allow Thorpe to draw on the $100 he has on deposit with the firm.
- T. C. Power & Co. (Helena, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe, 1879 August 31 (Folder 1)
  Letter ordering Thorpe to contract with Davis for the purchase of beef, subject to approval by Mr. Power himself.
- Joseph Thorpe (White's Gulch, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe, 1880 January 2 (Folder 1)
  Family news and instructions on getting a note made for sale of horses to Alonzo Ostrander.
- Rev. Frank B. Lewis (Bozeman, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe, 1880 February 9 (Folder 1)
  Letter inquiring over interest in Lewis leading a church service at Hamilton.
- John M. Sweeney (Helena, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe (Folder 1)
  Postscript to one of the earlier letters regarding agreement with William Perks.
- John M. Sweeney (Helena, Montana Territory) to Philip Thorpe (Folder 1)
  Letter regarding the Hay Ranch, and report on the Helena beef market.
- List of farm and ranch supplies (Folder 1)
- Fragment of revision to memoranda of agreement for William Perks (Folder 1)
- Fragment of financial notations (Folder 1)